(
"ai_sub_version": "3.6.0",
"generated_at": "2026-10-01T04:05:25.992149",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"service_tier": null,
"service_tier_subtitles": null,
"service_tier_lyrics": null,
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
のーーー…
Nooooo...
お主ら聞こえる？
Can you guys hear me?
のじゃー
Noja...
あれ？
Huh?
YouTube… 復活した？
Did YouTube... revive?
聞こえる？
Can you hear me?
大丈夫そう？
Does it look okay?
聞こえる！
I can hear you!
挨拶するのじゃ！
Time to greet!
あらあら
Oh my...
メラメラ
Mera-mera...
父上、メラ！
Father, Mera!
ホロライブ遊びまわりたいゴリアテ担当の引継ぎやさらマンダー！
Hologra wandering Goliath-in-charge Hiki-se-asaramander!
父上、メラなのじゃー！
Father, Mera, noja!
聞こえた？
Did you hear?
オッケー！
Okay!
大丈夫そう？
Does it look okay?
ちょっと心配なのじゃ。
I'm a bit worried.
なんかYouTubeが今妖怪ぜん… 妖怪前線じゃなくて、妖怪改善…w
It's like YouTube's current yokai... not yokai front, yokai improvement... lol
YouTubeに、あの今の主の配信の調子みたいなの、YouTubeからの今の電波とかの評価が妖怪… 妖怪改善になってるのじゃ！
It's like YouTube's evaluation of the current stream quality and signal has become 'yokai... yokai improvement'!
妖怪改善になってるのじゃ！
It's become yokai improvement!
どう？大丈夫かのう？
How is it? Is it okay?
聞こえる？大丈夫？
Can you hear? Is it okay?
大丈夫ならいいの。うん。
If it's okay, that's good. Yeah.
今日はお主何した？
What did you do today, master?
お仕事じゃった？
Was it work?
入り直したら行けた？
Did it work when you re-entered?
入り直して、入り直してほしいのじゃー！
Please re-enter, re-enter!
おみくじ引いた？ あ、そう！
Did you draw an omikuji? Oh, right!
ショート動画、ショート動画で、おみくじ出したのじゃ。
I put out an omikuji in a Short video.
秋葉でグッズ買った？やったのじゃー！
Did you buy merch in Akiba? Yay!
テスト期間なの、今？一発が大吉、すごい之じゃ！
Is it test season right now? The first one was Daikichi, amazing!
配信見るためだけに帰ってきた？わしのために？やったのじゃー！嬉しいのじゃー！
You came back just to watch the stream? For my sake? Yay! I'm so happy!
妖怪努力… 妖怪努力も入れてみたのじゃ。あの妖怪努力って言葉がめっちゃ好きで、
I tried adding 'Yokai effort'... I love the phrase 'Yokai effort'.
あの、あのわし『いそべいそべ物語』っていう漫画があっての、そう『いそべいそべ物語』って漫画が好きなんじゃが、そこにでてくる、あの妖怪努力ってのが超好きで、超好きで…
There's this manga called 'Isobe Isobe Monogatari', and I love that manga, and in it there's this 'Yokai effort' which I super love, super love...
あ、YouTube直った！非常にいいになってる！さっきまでなんか改善… よーく改善みたいなのが、非常にいいになってる！やったのじゃー！
Ah, YouTube fixed! It's become very good! Until just now, it was like 'improvement'... 'yook... improvement', but now it's become very good! Yay!
『磯部磯兵衛物語』にでてくる、あの将軍… 将軍じゃなくて、なんかお兄ちゃん恋巣磯兵衛みたいな…
In 'Isobe Isobe Monogatari', that Shogun... not Shogun, it's like Big Brother Koisu Isobee...
ごめんなのじゃ。ちょっときゅうきゅうに、きゅうにでて、きゅうにでてびっくりしたのじゃ。
Sorry. It suddenly came out, suddenly came out and surprised me.
ちょ、鼻水噛むからミュートさせてほしいのじゃ。…
Wait, I'm going to blow my nose so please let me mute...
今日ね、
So, um...
あの、わしがね、
You see...
あの、ごはんちゃんと食べてるかな、とかさ。
Like, whether I'm eating my meals properly...
お部屋ちゃんとお片付けられてるかなって。
Or if my room is kept clean...
あの、父親がね、人間の父親がね、わしのことを拾ってくれた人間の父親がね、
My dad—well, human parents, you know?
あの、おうち来てくれてね、お部屋片付けて、母が作ったごはんも持ってきてくれたのじゃ。
They come check on me, clean my room, and bring me food that my mom made, you know?
なんかデビュー前とかもね、
Even before my debut...
あの、やっぱ親というものは、この健康が心配みたいでの、
You know, parents are so worried about my health...
あの、ごはんをね、母がね作ってね、届けてくれるのじゃ。
that they'd make food and bring it to me, you know?
うん。おにぎりとか、から揚げとか、
They make things like onigiri, karaage...
作っての、ケーキとか作っての、
make cakes, and freeze them...
なんか冷凍しての、わしがの、食べるんじゃ。
and then I eat whatever washi wants, you know?
うん。優しいのじゃ。
They're so kind, you see.
そう、それでの、あのデビュー準備期間から今までも、
And so, ever since my debut preparation period until now...
なんかすごい、あの、今まで自分が思ったことないくらいパタパタしてての、
I've been so flustered, to the point I didn't even know what to think...
それでお部屋にダンボールの山ができてての。
and my room became a mountain of cardboard boxes, you know?
デビュー超前だったらダンボールとか指定してやったんだが、今ちょっとAmazonとかのダンボールでいっぱいになってての、
If it were just before my debut, I'd have had them specify things like Amazon...
それを父親がの、あの、一個ずつ折りたたんでの、片付けてくれたのじゃ。
It was my dad who folded them one by one and cleaned them up for me, you know?
うん。父親と母親はすごくわしのことを応援してくれてるのじゃ。
My mom and dad really support washi, you know?
うん。家族愛じゃの。
It's real family love, you think?
人間の家族愛じゃの、って思ったのじゃ。
Like, "Ah, this is human family love," I thought.
うん。父親と母親は人間なのだ。
My dad and mom are human, you see.
わしがあの、掲示板で痛い目を見て、山から下りて拾ってくれたのが父親と母親なのだ。
Washi saw painful things on the bulletin board, and my dad and mom went down the mountain to pick me up and rescue me.
人間の親、サラマンダーじゃないのじゃ。
They're human parents, not salamanders, you know?
わしは、犬を拾う感覚と近いと思って戴ければ、わしは拾われたサラマンダーなのだ。
You could say it's close to the feeling of rescuing a dog, and washi is a rescued salamander, you see.
きょうだい、ひとりっこなのだ。
An only child, you see.
優しい人間がわしのこと拾ってくれましたのだ。
A kind human picked washi up, you see.
そう、種族違うけど父親と母親優しくしてくれて凄いのじゃ。
Species are different, but it's amazing how kind my dad and mom are to me, you know?
本当のご両親、わしのことを生んだサラマンダーの親は知らないのじゃ、あったことないのじゃ、認識もしてないのじゃ。
The salamander who gave birth to washi—my true parents—doesn't even know me, has never met me, and doesn't even recognize me, you see.
ましてどうやって生まれたんじゃろ。
Washi wonders how I was even born, though.
お父さんとお母さん配信見てる?配信はなんか見てるっぽ、はははは。
Do my dad and mom watch my stream? Well, it seems like they watch it, hahaha.
でも父親も母親もSNSやってないから、なんか全然あんまりわかんないじゃん。アカウントとか持ってないんだが、それでもなんかこう、検索？
It seems they look things up using search engines, since they don't use SNS, you see.
検索とかで見てくれてるっぽいのじゃ。
They seem to look it up using search, you know.
見られてるのじゃ。全部見てるかはわからないけど、なんか、すごかった、なんか動画、初配信の動画、すごかったって褒めてくれたのじゃ。
They've seen it, right? And they've praised my videos, saying my first stream's video was amazing, you know.
そして、今日は空気読みというゲームで遊ばせていただこうと思いますのじゃあ。
And today, I'd like to play a game called "Kuukiyomi" (Consider It), you see.
わし、サラマンダーだから人間のコミュニケーションにあまり自信がなくて、
Since washi is a salamander, I don't have much confidence in human communication...
人間社会への溶け込みにあまり自信がなくて、
and I'm not very confident about blending into human society, you see.
デビュー前とかも、そのホロライブの先輩とか遊びまわりたいのメンバーとかと仲良くなるために道徳の教科書とかいっぱいいろ読んで勉強したんじゃが、
Before my debut, I read lots of morals textbooks to get along with Hololive seniors and members I want to hang out with, you see.
それでもまだ人間社会のこと分かりきってない気がする。
Even so, I still feel like I haven't quite figured out human society yet, you know.
でも、道徳の教科書読んだのじゃ。NASA-san読んで、なるほどと人間について知ったのじゃ。
Still, I read morals textbooks, NASA-san's books, and learned a lot about humans, you see.
だから、
So...
今日は
Today,
その成果を
I'll show you...
サラマンダーとして生きてきたが、人間社会にわしこれぐらい溶け込めますよっていう成果を
how a salamander has lived in human society.
お主らに見せようと。甘いマシナじゃ。
I'll show you all, so praise me!
hey mola
お主ら、
Hey Onushira,
やっぱ仮面外してほしい?
y'all want me to take off the mask?
[笑い声]
Hehehehe!
おめ、おめ外してほしい?
You want me to take it off?
見たいのじゃ?
You want to see?
見たい?
You want to?
You want to see?
どうなるのじゃ?
What's going to happen?
見たかったら
If you want to see it,
高評価してほしいのじゃ、お願いなのじゃ、
please high-evaluate it, I'm begging you!
人間にしてほしいのじゃあ。
Turn me into a human!
してぇ?
You doing it?
やったのじゃあ!
You did it, Onushira!
2回目は押しちゃいなくていいのじゃ。
Twice is no good.
なくなっちゃう。
It'll disappear.
1回だけ押してほしいのじゃ。
I want you to press it just once.
押しとる?した?
Did you press it? Did you?
やったのじゃあ!奇数回、
You did it, Onushira! Odd times,
奇数回押してほしいのじゃ。
press an odd number of times, I'm begging you.
よし、
Alright,
じゃあお主らがいっぱい高評価してくれたみたいじゃから、
so Onushira seems to have given a lot of high evaluations,
わしもお面を外して
I will also take off my mask
ゲームを始めるとしますのじゃあ!
and start the game!
ちょっと遅かった。
That was a bit slow.
ちょっと遅かったのじゃ。
That was a bit slow, Onushira.
おしながき。
Menu.
空気読み。
Read the Room.
サクッと空気読み。
Quickly Read the Room.
ふたりで空気読み。
Read the Room with Two.
オプション
Options.
どうじゃろか。
How should I do this?
音でかいかの?
Is the sound too loud?
BGMの音量とかがどうかを、お主らに聞きたいんじゃが、
I want to ask Onushira if the BGM volume and such are okay,
おっき?
Is it big?
これぐらいなら、いい?
Is it good if it's about this much?
ちっちゃい?
Is it small?
バランスどうなのじゃ?
How's the balance?
そもそも聞こえておるかの?
Can you even hear it in the first place?
どうかの?
How is it?
元のBGM残ってる?はっ。
Is the original BGM remaining? Ah.
どう?戻せた。
How is it? I was able to put it back.
これでいいんじゃない?
Isn't this fine?
これで、これでいいんじゃない?
Is this, is this fine?
どうなのじゃ?直った?
How is it? Is it fixed?
これいいんじゃない?
Isn't this fine?
どうじゃどうじゃ?
How is it, how is it?
ちっちゃい?
Small?
態度が小さい?え、それはいいことなのじゃ。
Attitude is small? Eh, isn't that a good thing, Onushira?
それいいんじゃない?
Isn't that good?
いい感じ?
Good feeling?
いい感じそうかの?
Seems like a good feeling?
ちょっとあの、まだ新人のうちはちょっとこういうのいっぱいお主らに聞くかもしれないけど、
I might ask Onushira a lot of things while I'm still new,
教えてくれると嬉しいですのじゃ。
so I'd be happy if you could teach me!
態度でかくしてほしい?
You want my attitude to be bigger?
でも空気を読めないよ、そしたら。
Even though I can't read the room?
空気を読むためにはやはり謙虚にいかなきゃいけない?
To read the room, do I have to be modest?
どうかの?
How is it?
よし。
Alright.
それじゃあ、空気読みを
Then, let's read the room!
ゲームBGMちょっち小さい、了解なのじゃ。
Game BGM is a bit small, understood, Onushira.
もくもくもく。
Mokumokumoku.
どう?
How is it?
でかすぎ?
Too big?
上げすぎ?
Too high?
あ、消えた。
Ah, it disappeared.
上げすぎ?
Too high?
いい感じ。
Good feeling.
よし。
Alright.
それじゃあ、わしの空気読み、行きますのじゃあ!
Then, I'll go read the room, Onushira!
どのボタンかあの、これ!
Which button is it? This?
これでいけるんじゃない?
This will work, right?
ここは自由に空気を読んでよい空間。あなたが空気を読むことを止める人は誰もいません。
Here is a space where you can freely read the room. No one will stop you from reading the room.
空気を読むことを止める人がいる空間があるのじゃ。
There is a space where someone stops you from reading the room.
人間社会ってむずいのじゃ。なんか空気読むのが逆にダメ、逆の逆みたいなのもあるのじゃ、トラップなのじゃ。
Human society is tough, you know? Like, reading the room is actually bad, the reverse of the reverse kind of thing also exists, it's a trap, you know?
たった1人で空気が読める夢の世界。心ゆくまでご堪能下さい。なるほど。
Please enjoy the dream world where only one person can read the room to your heart's content. I see.
やっていくのじゃあ!
Let's do it!
画面内の赤いのを動かす事で空気を読め。
Read the room by moving the red thing on the screen.
そうじゃない場合もあるが、そこは空気を読んで違う行動をとれ。
There are cases where that's not the case, but in that case, read the room and take a different action.
中断したい時はESCキーを押せ。了解なのだ。
When you want to interrupt, press the ESC key, understood.
操作方法の説明。始まった、第1問!
Explanation of operation method. Question 1 has started!
電車。
Train.
ん?
Huh?
何?何が起きてるのじゃ?
What? What is happening?
あ、あ、あ、こういうことね!こういうお、お座り系ね!
Ah, ah, ah, like this, right? Like this seating kind of...
なるほど、何が起きているかを瞬時に判断しなきゃいけないんじゃな?
I see, you have to instantly judge what is happening.
小学生ドミノの、あ、小学生、子供のね、子供に成功体験を積
Elementary school domino, ah, elementary school, children's, you know, putting a success experience for children...
大事ななのじゃ。成功体験を積めなかった子供は
...and that's important. Children who don't experience success
後になって後になってそれが一生、一生執着してしまうのじゃ。ふせ！
grow up, and eventually become obsessed with it. Stay!
え、人間ジラされるの好きって聞いた。ジラしてみるのじゃ。ジラ、あ、ジラす
I heard people like being toyed with. Let's try to toy with them.
でしょ。でもこれも好きなんじゃろ人間。こういうのが、そしたらさ
Well, humans probably like this kind of thing, too.
バカじゃん。あ、後ろに人いる。え、でもこれはし知ってるのじゃ。右側歩いちゃダメなのだじゃ。
"You're an idiot." Oh, there's someone behind them.
エスカレーターはね、歩くと危ないからね。こうすることでね、治安をね守っていますのだじゃ。
Escalators are dangerous to walk on, so doing this protects safety.
これは正しいと思うじゃ。カモメ、あ、鳥が
This one's correct, right? Birds...
え、これバズる！これTwitterにあげたらバズるのだじゃ！これで満バズするのだじゃ！
Oh, this is buzzworthy! If you post this on Twitter, it'll buzz!
人間！人間今写真撮るのだじゃ！写真撮って、
Human! Humans, take a picture right now!
写真撮ってTwitter上げて50万バズするのだじゃ。そこはかとなく
Take a picture and post it to Twitter for 500,000 likes!
読めてるっぽい。これ褒められたわし？わし褒められた？いいてこと？
Reading into it? Does that mean it's good?
いいてことかな？あの写真満バズするじゃろうな。
That photo is definitely going to buzz!
あ、サンタさん！
Ah, Santa Claus!
えっと、寝る。
Sleeping.
やっぱあの、こういうのって、建て前同士がね、大人も子供もそれぞれバカし合ってきている。信じられる？
See, adults and children both act like fools. Unbelievable.
し、あー次。ご注文は？
Next! Question 5!
生、生、生、生で。
Draft beer, draft beer, draft beer, draft beer.
え？でもれいわじゃよ今。ウーロンちゃなのだじゃ。
What? But the order is... Oolong tea now!
ウーロンちゃん飲みたいのじゃ。ウーロンちゃん飲みたい。洗濯押せないのだじゃ。
I want to see Oolong tea! I want to see Oolong tea!
どこって洗濯押す？どこなら押せる？
Where do I press? Which one can I press?
え？選択できなかった！
Eh? I couldn't select it!
わし悪い？サラマンダー？選べなかったのだじゃ。
Was my choice bad? Couldn't choose salamander?
AちゃんとBちゃんとCちゃんがいるのだじゃ。
A, B, and C are here.
何？あ、止まった。のだじゃ。
What? Oh, stopped.
何？何？今、今何が起きた？今、今何？今何が起きたのだじゃ？
What? What? What just happened? What just happened?
AちゃんとBちゃんとCちゃん、A、B、C。あ、人を選ぶ？
A, B, C, A, B, C. Oh, choosing a person?
え、選ばれない人を選ぶみたいな。でもそれは妥協だと、なんかそれは良くないのだじゃ。
Like, choosing the person who wasn't chosen. But that's a compromise, and that's not good.
選ばれないからという理由で選ばれた人は本当に選ばれた人嬉しくないと思うのじゃ。
Because they aren't chosen, the person who gets chosen will really be happy.
この最後のピンを倒せたら付き合ってください。
If you can knock down this last pin, I'll go out with you.
うん、いいよ。
Yeah, okay.
倒れないのだじゃ！こんなんで！
It won't fall! With this kind of...
こんなんで自分の意思を他人に委ねるやつに倒れるのために倒れるわけにはいかないのだじゃ。
Leaving your own will to someone else is no reason to fall!
やっぱ、あの、自分のせのね、なんか他人にね、最終的な判断を委ねるってのはね、良くないのだじゃ。弱さなのだじゃ。
You know, leaving your final judgment to someone else is weak and no good.
ダメなのだじゃ。
That's no good.
そんな、そんな弱さで、そんな生半可な気持ちで付き合うって言われた言われて本当にCちゃんは喜ぶか？
If someone tells you to go out with them with such weak, half-hearted feelings, would C be happy?
喜ばないと思うのじゃ。人間の弱さなのだじゃ。
I don't think they'd be happy. It's human weakness.
厳しい。厳しい。
Strict. Strict.
人間はこういうのもダメ？人間？
Human, is this no good either? Human...
え？でも、でもそれって本当にその人のためになるのかの？
Eh? But is that really for that person's benefit?
なんか、わし思うんじゃが、わし思うんじゃが。えらいけどゲーム違う？
I think, I think... Oh, but this is a game, right?
そっか、ゲームの趣旨みたいなのもある？
Oh right, is this the moral of the game too?
む、難しいのだじゃ。でもここ、ここでゲームだからと言って自分の意思を曲げてしまったら
That's tricky. But if you bend your own will just because it's a game,
それが一生続いちゃう気がするのだじゃ。なんかワールドトリガーで言ってたのじゃ。
it feels like it will last forever. World Trigger said something like that.
ワールドトリガーでこんなセリフがあった気がするのだじゃ。1回でも曲げちゃダメなのだじゃ。
World Trigger had a line like that. You shouldn't bend it, not even once.
次行くのだじゃ！
Let's go to the next one!
よし。
Alright.
行くのだじゃ。起立！
Let's go. Rise!
これ何？なんか流れてきた。
What is this? Something is flowing down.
ん、つぶすけ？えい！
Crush them? Hey!
これ、目を肥やしてこと？
Nourish your eyes, is that it?
えい！何これ、目を肥やせ？
Hey! What is this? Nourish your eyes?
これ何が正しいのだじゃ？これ何？目を肥やせ？
What is correct here? What is this? Nourish your eyes?
ゲーム、ミニゲーム入ったのだじゃ。のだじゃ。
A game, a mini-game is included. Noda?
礼！礼！ 着席！
Bow! Bow! Sit down!
まち、和を乱してはいけないのだじゃ。人間社会。
Wait, you shouldn't cause harmony. Human society.
彼女と動物園に来ました。デート！
I came to the zoo with my girlfriend. Date!
何？禁止って書いてるのだじゃ。危ない？
What? It says "Prohibited". Is it dangerous?
スマホ見てるのだじゃ。幽霊寂しがってる。構ってあげよう。
Looking at the smartphone. The ghost is feeling lonely, let's comfort them.
うわ！、驚かせてあげるというやつね。幽霊にも優しい。
Woah! Surprise them! That kind of thing. Gentle to ghosts too.
えい、ウェーブなのだじゃ、ウェーブ。
Wave! It's a wave!
こういうのめっちゃやってみたいのだじゃ。遊びまわりたいやりたいのだじゃ。
I really want to try doing this. I want to participate in real life too.
4人だと少ないかも。4人だと少ないかも。
Four people might be too few. Four people might be too few.
これ好きなのだじゃ。わしもやりたい！
I like this! I want to do it too!
わしもやりたーい
I want to do it too!
ふん、ふん。
Hmm, hmm.
空気読み分かってきた。ほどよく読めてるっぽい。
I'm starting to get how to read the room. Seems like I'm reading things pretty well.
え、これわし、わしなかなか、わしなかなか
Wait, me... I'm actually pretty—I'm actually...
あの、人間社会でやっていけそうじゃない？
You know, like I could make it in human society?
人間社会でやっていけそうな感じするのじゃ。ま、稼げるのじゃ。
I feel like I'd do fine in human society. Well, I can earn a living.
第16問。
Question 16.
雨降ってる。
It's raining.
傘差してる。
Holding an umbrella.
あ、こういう系ね。避ける系。わしこういうのめっちゃ避けるのじゃ。
Ah, this kind of thing. Avoiding things. I'm really good at avoiding stuff like this.
傘の先っちょって怖くない？
Aren't umbrella tips scary?
傘の先っちょ怖いから
Umbrella tips are scary, so
傘持つときは下に向けて持ってるのじゃ。
when I hold an umbrella, I point it downwards.
次のバス停でおりる僕です。
"I'm the one getting off at the next bus stop."
バス停了解？
Bus stop acknowledged?
次は終点、中野車庫。
Next is the final stop, Nakano Depot.
終点、終点ならおさなくていいのじゃ。
Final stop—if it's the final stop, you don't need to press it.
終点ならおさなくていいのじゃ。んなのじゃ。
If it's the final stop, you don't need to press it. That's right.
第18問。
Question 18.
あー、ポール歩く系ね。
Ah, walking by poles.
ポールあるならどかないかもななのじゃ。ポールあるならどかないかもななのじゃ。
If there's a pole, maybe I don't move out of the way. If there's a pole, maybe I don't move.
今日は彼女とデートだ！
Today's a date with my girlfriend!
いや、わしが左にずれればよかったのでは？気づかなかった。デートだってデート！
Wait, shouldn't I have shifted to the left? I didn't notice. It's a date!
おなごは恋愛映画が見たいけど、わしはロボットアニメが見たい？えー、あ、あー
She wants to see a romance movie, but I want to see a robot anime? Uh, oh...
優秀不発になってたら、どちらにも、どちらにも行けなく。
If it's a dud, you can't go anywhere.
あ、あ、なんかおなごが通路が、通路がシャドウ歩いてる。でもわし、わし、もう怖いから一緒に、そのときは一緒に受け入れよう。
Ah, um, looks like she's walking on the shadow side of the aisle. But I'm, I'm scared, so I'll just accept it together with her at that time.
このあきらめよう。
I'll just give up on this.
ちょ、むずい！空気読みむずいのじゃ！
Man, it's hard! Reading the room is so hard!
むずい、むずい。ど、どう？
Hard, hard. What, how?
え、だってわしさ、これサママンダーあるあるなんじゃが、
I mean, for me, this is a salamander thing, but
あの、電車のね、ホーム歩くときね、電車側怖いから、できるだけ中側通りたいのじゃ。
when walking on train platforms, the train side is scary, so I want to walk on the inner side as much as possible.
シャドウでも同様。シャドウでも同様。できるだけ
Same for shade. Same for shade. As much as possible
信号待つときもできるだけシャドウ側じゃない奥の方で待つんじゃが、ちょ、怖いのじゃ。
when waiting for traffic lights, I wait further back, not on the shady side, but it's kinda scary.
もうダメなときはダメなのじゃ。諦めるのじゃ。
When it's no good, it's no good. Gotta give up.
次ののじゃ。
Next one.
21問。
Question 21.
あ、おはようございます。
Ah, good morning.
あ、あ、あ、あ、あ、こ、これは、これは、あの、反応しちゃうと、あの、社内政治が危ういやつ。
Ah, ah, ah, th-this is one of those things where if you react, office politics get dangerous.
わし知ってるのじゃ！
I know about this!
第22問。
Question 22.
あ、目に入らんのか！入ります、入ります！あのいくらでも、頭下がり、あの、自分が下ですと、あの、後輩ムーブをかますのじゃ。
Ah, you don't notice me?! I notice you, I notice you! I'll bow my head as much as it takes, pulling a junior move showing I'm below you.
第23問。
Question 23.
やはり人間社会で生き延びるということ早い。歩くの早いの一じゃ。ちょ、お主！お主！お主！
Surviving in human society means being fast. Walking fast. Hey, you! You! You!
歩く速度合わすのじゃ。シャドウ側は、シャドウ側は嫌じゃけど、歩く速度ぐらいはいくらでも合わせるのじゃ。
Match your walking speed. I hate the shady side, but I can at least match your walking speed.
第24問。
Question 24.
後輩はね、やはり後輩という強い意志を。今日はデートです。そろそろ彼氏と思っていいのかな。
A junior has a strong will to stay a junior. Today is a date. Wonder if I can think of him as my boyfriend soon.
え、彼氏じゃないのにデートなのはじゃ？
Wait, it's a date even though he's not my boyfriend?
アニメを見に行くことにするので恋愛映画にさせましたがが、
I wanted to go see an anime, but ended up going with a romance movie, though
男の子って本当空気読めない。彼ったら勇気を出して手をつないで来た。あら、やるじゃないの。
Boys really don't read the room. He mustered up the courage and held my hand. Oh, not bad.
もう私たち付き合ってるよね。これはどうなのはじゃ？
We're already going out, right? How is this?
そしてチューしてるチュー！あ、ほ、こういうこと？
And they're kissing! Ah, oh, like this?
い、いい空気にしちゃう的ナン？
Making it into a good atmosphere or something?
第25問。
Question 25.
恋愛映画見てこれするの、本当にいるの？
Do people really do this after watching a romance movie?
本当にこういうの有るの？知らないのじゃ！
Does this really happen? I don't know!
え、え、なんかチューチューしてるのじゃ、え、え、よ、み、見ないフリ、見ないフリ、気づかないフリのじゃー！
Uh, uh, they're kissing... uh, uh, pr-pretend not to see, pretend not to see, pretend not to notice!
あからさまに。が、が、頑ミしてやってもよかったな。頑ミしてやってもよかったのじゃ。
Obviously. I should've just stared hard at them. I should've stared hard at them.
ちょ、こ、行動ですよ！行動ですよお主ら！お主らここは行動ですつって、公共の、公共の道路ですよつって。
Hey, this is a public act! Public act, you guys! You guys, this is a public place, and a public road, you know!
頑ミしてやってもぶつかる？ぶつかる？そこまではそこまでは別に悪いことされたわけじゃないし、ぶつかるのは炎上しちゃうのじゃ。
Even if you stare, you crash? Crash? Well, it's not like they did anything particularly wrong, and crashing would cause a firestorm.
もしその、あのカップルを、あの行動でチューしてるカップルいて笑ろたっていう動画を撮ってTwitterに上げてある悪いいたとして、
If there was some bad person who filmed a video saying "Look at this couple kissing in public, lol" and posted it on Twitter,
わしがそこにぶっかっていったら大炎上ですのじゃ。だから良くないのじゃ。ぶつからないのじゃ。
and I crashed right into them, it'd be a huge controversy. So that's no good. Don't crash.
人にぶつからないようにわしとか特にね、
Especially for me, not crashing into people—
どうしたらいいのじゃ？どうしたらいいのじゃ？
What should I do? Is this okay?
なんか、ホロメンだけなまえの色、ピカピカのレインボーとかにできないの？
Can't I make the whole thing a shiny, rainbow color?
ピカピカのレインボーとかじゃったら大丈夫なんじゃが、同じ色じゃからわかんないのじゃ。ざこ！
If it were a shiny rainbow, it'd be fine, but since it's the same color, I don't know! Sucker!
あ、痛っ！ツズリなのじゃ！
Ah, it hurts! Tsuzuri, is it?
ツズリ、わしの人間適応力を…
Tsuzuri, reading human reading comprehension...
恐れおののきながら、見るのがよいのじゃ。
Well, it's better to read it with some fear.
監督: 誰がイエロー役をやってくれるかな？
"Director: Who will play Yellow?"
え、はいはいはい！やるやるやるやるやる！
"Eh, yes, yes, yes! I'll do it, I'll do it, I'll do it!"
イエローと言えば、イエローと言えば食いしん坊。なんかそういうイメージがあるのじゃ。え、違うかも？
Speaking of yellow, I think of gluttony. Is that wrong?
なんでみんなあげないのじゃ？オーディションって。
Why isn't everyone raising their hands? An audition?
イエロー！じゃーん！超かっこいい！爆発なのじゃーー！レンジャー演出なのじゃーー！
Yellow! Bam! So cool! It's an explosion, a Ranger production!
わしレンジャーもちょっと見てたよ。なんじゃっけ？激レンジャー？
I was watching Ranger a bit too. What was it? Hyper Ranger?
にゃんにゃん？
Nyan-nyan?
何？テトリスなのじゃ。
What? It's Tetris!
これで合ってる？合ってる？
Is this right? Is it right?
え？のじゃ？
Eh? Is that right?
脳内いらないで君のを見てあげるね。まあ、楽しみ。
"No need to read ahead, I'll read yours for you." Well, I'm looking forward to it.
あ、なんか占いコンテンツ。はっ！
Ah, some kind of fortune-telling content. Ha!
まあ、人間とは繁殖を望む個体もいると聞くから、そんなにおかしいことではないのではないではないかと思うのじゃ。
Well, I hear humans also want to reproduce, so it's not that weird, right?
長生き。右向け右！
Long-Aki. Right, face right!
ふっ！
Hmm.
え？合ってる？右？
Eh? Is that right? Right?
なんとはなしに読めてるっぽい。ふむふむ。ふむふむふむ。
"It was nothing at all... Looks readable." Hmm, hmm.
いけるのじゃ。
Can I go?
なんか行けそう。わしなんか、え、これ左？なんで？
It seems like I can. Wait, is this left? Why?
はっ！ん？わしから見て右。ん？
Ha! Hmm? From my perspective, right?
わしから見て、右。
From my perspective, right?
わ、お主から見ると、
Wait, from the owner's perspective?
ん？左？ん？
Hmm? Left? Hmm?
次行くのじゃ！ふん。むずいのじゃ。
Let's go next! Hmm. This is hard.
31問。
Question 31.
お前。
You.
バーバー、バー。バーバーってなんのじゃ？
Barber, Bar. What does "Bar-Bar" mean?
バーバー？
Barber?
バーバーって何？
What is "bar-bar"?
バー。
Bar.
バーバー、とこや？
Barber is a barbershop?
何？のじゃ。
What? No way.
32。あ、あ、これやりたい！ねえ、これやりたい！あー！
32. Ah, ah, I want to do this! Hey, I want to do this!
遅い！遅い！遅い！遅い！遅い！あ、瞬発力！あ、はははは！
Too late, too late, too late, too late, too late! Ah, quick reflexes!
ちょ、かっこいいって思ったら、かっこいいのじゃって思ったら、時が、あ。
Wait, I thought it was cool, so I thought "How cool of you," and then...
キミが手術に勝てるように明日の試合ホームランを撃つぞ。
"Hoping you win your surgery tomorrow, I'll hit a home run for you..."
ん？
Hmm?
来た！
It's coming!
ドミニカの大砲でらっさん、のじゃー！あ！
Dominican cannonball, here it comes! No way! Ah!
わしのプレイスキルが低いあまりに。気持ち的には、あ、はははははは！
My play skills are too low. Emotionally, I...
ははははは！
Ha, ha, ha, ha!
なんかプレイスキル、あの空気読み！空気読みあり！空気読み終わりなのに！
Play skill, the air-reading! Air-reading is available! Air-reading is over!
これが最後のボールだ絶対に逃してはくない…！
"This is the last ball! I must not miss..."
これが最後のボールだ絶対に逃してなくちゃ！来た来た！来るぞ！
It's the last ball! Don't miss it! It's coming, it's coming! It's going to hit!
よいしょ！
Here we go!
はあ…むずいのじゃ。
Ha... It's hard!
そして？
And then?
そして？あー、むずいのじゃ。
And then? Ah, it's hard!
なんか、なんか
It's hard.
空気読み、気持ち、気持ちは、気持ちはあるのに！気持ちはあるのに！気持ちはあるのに！あの届かない。
Air-reading, feelings, feelings are, feelings are there, but feelings are there, but I can't reach it.
あと一歩が、あと一歩が届かない。
One more step, one more step away.
判断が遅い！のじゃ！行くのじゃ！
Judgment is slow! No way! Let's go!
むずいのじゃー！
It's hard!
36問。あ、あ、苦手なやつ。行くよ、行くよ！よいしょ！あー！
36. Ah, ah, that thing I'm bad at. Here we go, here we go, here we go!
あー！
Ah.
苦手なのじゃ。なわとび。
I'm bad at it. Jump rope.
あ、す、す、座ります。夜露死苦！あてじなのじゃ。
Ah, s-s-sit down. "Best regards." Readably.
ふん。まだやれるのじゃ。
Hmm. Still can't do it.
何？あ！
What? Ah.
か、かきゅう、かきゅう、かきゅう、かきゅう！ん？何？ん？
Ca- c-shot, c-shot, c-shot, c-shot! Hmm? What? Hmm?
な、な、な、今のはわし何するべきじゃった？
N- n- n- what should I do now?
寝てる。
Sleeping.
寝てる。あ、逃げる。
Sleeping. Ah. Running away.
逃げる逃げる逃げる逃げる逃げる逃げる逃げる。あ、立ってる？座る座る座る。
Running, running, running, running, running, running, running. Ah, standing? Sit, sit, sit.
寄りかかんないで燃えちゃう。燃えちゃうのじゃ。
Don't get too close or I'll burn. I'm going to burn.
お手を拝借？
Borrowing a pose?
拝借！よーっ、ぽん！
Borrowing! Yo, pong!
ちょっと遅い。
A bit late.
プレースキル自信なし。
P-Play skills... no confidence.
ねぇ、音ゲー？
You know, rhythm games...
音ゲー難しい？
Rhythm games are difficult, right?
プレーースキル自信なし。
Play skills, no confidence.
なんかいつもちょっと遅いのじゃ。
I'm always a bit slow with them.
でも気持ちは、気持ちは...
I mean, the feeling is there,
あるし、何やるかはわかるんじゃけど、
and I know what I should do,
リズム天国心配になってきたのじゃ。
I'm getting worried about rhythm heaven.
キャプボナウだからやりたいけど心配になってきたのじゃ。
I want to do Capelybon, but I'm worried.
第41問。
Question 41.
のじゃ。
Now then.
あ、スカートの中見えちゃって危ない。
Oh, her skirt is showing, that's dangerous.
あ、スカート隠すのじゃ。
Oh, she should pull her skirt down.
スカートの中見えちゃう。
Her skirt is showing.
女の子、電車の中寝る時危ないのじゃ。
It's dangerous for a girl sleeping on a train.
第42問。
Question 42.
今日は大好きなアイドル「A子」の握手会...
Today is the handshake event for my favorite idol, A-ko...
いや、これでするの...
Wait, wouldn't buying it...
全員みたいにして、失礼、失礼じゃろ。
That's just rude to everyone!
これで、これでB子の人気がないからってB子に行ったらそれは失礼じゃろ。演者に対して、本気でやってるんじゃから。
And if you go to B-ko when she has no popularity, that's rude to the performer, since they're doing it seriously.
何々何々？
What, what, what?
あ、大きくなるキノコ。
Oh, a mushroom that makes you bigger.
ジャンプ！
Jump!
人間 一緒の 思いやり 足並みを 揃えて。
Humans share the same empathy and pace.
第44問。
Question 44.
カメラ撮っている。
She's taking a photo.
なんでそんなアングルなのじゃ？
Why that angle?
なんでそんなアングル？のじゃ？
な、何が起きてるの？
Wait, what is happening?
第45問。
Question 45.
何が起きてたの？
What just happened?
この部屋少し寒くない？ 了解。
"This room is a bit cold, isn't it?" "Understood."
寒いから上げるのじゃ。
It's cold, so I'll turn it up.
温度。
Temperature...
上げ上げ上げ上げ上げ。
Up, up, up, up, up.
どれぐらいがいいんじゃろうな、寒いて。
I wonder what's a good temperature for "cold"?
これぐらいか。の。
Around this much?
慣れてるっぽい。
It looks like she's getting used to it.
なるほどなのじゃ。分かってきた。
Ah, I see, I see.
分かってきた。
I've got it.
え、暑い？
Wait, is it hot?
どれぐらいに上げるのがいいのじゃ？
How much should I turn it up?
冷房。
Air conditioning...
切るの、あ、切ればよかったのかな？
Should I have just turned it off?
上げないで切ればよかったのかな？
Would it have been better to just turn it off without turning it up?
人間の適性温度が分かんないのじゃ。
I don't know the proper temperature for humans.
人間はどれぐらいの温度だと心地いいか分かんないのじゃ。
I wonder what temperature makes humans feel comfortable.
いつも和式順で部屋の温度設定してオルから、サラマンダーにはわかんないのじゃ。
I always set my room temperature based on Washiki, so I don't know about Salamander.
その辺は人間の体のことはもうちょい勉強しなきゃいけないの。
I need to study more about human bodies.
いくのじゃ。
Let's go.
第46問。
Question 46.
本読んでる。
Reading a book.
あ、ジャンプ読んでる。
Ah, she's reading a magazine.
立ち読みめっちゃいるのじゃ。
She's reading over her shoulder.
立ち読みっていいの？
Is it okay to read over someone's shoulder?
あ、子供に成功体験を積ませるのじゃー！
Ah, she gets a succession of kids.
成功体験って大事なのじゃ。
Succession experiences are important.
暑い。あー、ノドかわいた～ついでにコーヒー買ってきてよ。 了解。
"It's hot. Oh, I'm thirsty. Get me some coffee on the way." "Understood."
コーヒー。
Coffee.
ノドか、熱そう。
Thirsty. Hot looks good.
でもホットしかないよ。
But they only have hot.
でも女の子は言う通りにしないと怒るから、コールドのものを買っても意味ないのじゃ。
Buying cold drinks is useless since the girl gets mad if you don't do as she says.
コーヒーって言ったよねって絶対言われるのじゃ。
She'll definitely say, "I said coffee!"
でも、あの暑いと言っても絶対怒られるから、それはもう覚悟、覚悟をするのじゃ。
But she'll also get mad if it's hot, so you just have to be prepared.
あ、この子にあげよ。主人あげるよ。
I'll give it to this girl.
女の子何してもキレるから、
The girl gets mad no matter what,
とりあえず言う通りを優先にするのじゃ。
so you prioritize doing as she says.
緊急特番！驚異の気功術！！
Emergency Special: Amazing Telekinesis!
あーー！
Ah...
うわーー！
Woah!
エンタメが分かるサラマンダーレシのじゃ。
That's a salamander that's good at entertainment.
まあ、わしバーチャルじゃからの、
Well, I'm a VTuber,
エンタメに強い、エンタメに強いのじゃ。
so I'm strong at entertainment.
え、何してもキレるのじゃ。キレる時は何してもキレるから、
Well, she gets mad no matter what,
うん、まあ2個買うのが本当いいのじゃ。冷たいのとコーヒーも両方買うのじゃ。
so buying two is the real answer—cold and coffee, buying both.
やらせ？
Right?
でも見てる主人が楽しい方が良いのじゃ。
Well, watching the owner get flustered is more fun.
楽しませられた人が勝ちなのじゃ。
The person who makes it fun wins.
いくのじゃ。
Let's go.
51。
51.
何？
What?
え、それは良くないのじゃ。
Hey, that's not good.
それは本当に良くないのじゃ。今のご時世もっと良くないのじゃ。
That's really not good. This situation is even worse.
ちょ、ちょ、ちょ、気を付けるのじゃー！
You gotta be careful.
炎上しちゃう。
I'm gonna get cancelled.
日の神様じゃ、日の神様じゃ！だったらダメなのじゃー！
Sun's grace, sun's grace! Otherwise it's no good!
何？
What?
何何何何見とる？
What are they doing?
な、な、なんなのじゃ？
What, what is this?
人間、人間人の視野、視野を。
Human, human's field of view.
何？
What?
あ、泥が、泥が。ちょ止まる。
Ah, mud, mud. Stop for a bit.
ちょ人間にかけちゃ良くないのじゃ。
Splashing humans isn't good.
でも後ろも困るかな、突っかえて。
Though backing up would be troublesome too.
よしよ。
Alright.
「お兄ちゃん、お腹すいた」「お兄ちゃんがなんとかするからがんばるんだぞ…」
"Big brother, I'm hungry." "Big brother will take care of it, so hang in there!"
あみだ大会 決勝！！
Amida Lottery Finals!!
勝ったほうが焼肉食べ放題！！
The winner gets all-you-can-eat yakiniku!!
線は書かなくても書かなくてもいい。
The drawer of the line doesn't even need to write it.
ええと、今、今、ちょっと待って計算ができない。
Um, now, now, wait, I can't calculate this.
あん、に、ん、どうなる？
An, ni... how does this go?
待て、待て、ちょ、待て、ゆっくり、ゆっくり考えさせて。
Wait, wait, hold on, let me think slowly.
1、2、3、4、あ、引く、引く、引くといい、引くといい。
1, 2, 3, 4, ah, drawing is good.
よしよしよしよし、いや、むずいのはじゃ、考えるのむずいのはじゃ。
Man, figuring this out is tough.
合ってたかな？合ってたかの？
Was that right? Was it correct?
ちょ、むずいのはじゃ、こういう処理能力自信なし。
Man, this is tough, I'm bad at this kind of processing.
え、何？なんか恥ずかしがってる。
Eh, what? It looks embarrassed.
褒める的な？あ、隠してあげる的な？
Like praising? Ah, like hiding it?
これ？あ、さっきできなかったやつそれか！
This? Ah, the one I couldn't do earlier, so that's it!
さっき腕がないのってそれか！理解したのじゃ。
So that's why it didn't have arms earlier! I understand now.
難しい。これゲームなのじゃ、ゲーム。
This is difficult. It's a game, a game.
あからさまに……読めてるっぽい。
"Overtly..." ...looks like it can be read.
え、あからさまにってかなり、かなり読めてる切なくない？
Isn't "overtly" pretty readable and heartbreaking?
わしすごくないない？わしサラマンダーとは思えないんじゃない？
Isn't that amazing? Can't you believe I'm a salamander?
もうまるで人間、まるで人間なんじゃなかろうかと思うんじゃが。
I think I'm practically human at this point.
わかってきたのじゃ。
I'm starting to get it.
かなり、かなりの久しぶりに脳内占いで、のぞいて見るかね。
For quite a long time, let's check out a brain fortune-telling.
出たのじゃ。ででん。何？
It came out. Ta-da. What?
何これ？ゴミ？ゴミ捨てるのじゃ。
What is this? Garbage? I'm throwing away garbage.
ゴミ、どうやって捨てるのがいいのかな？あ、隠れた。
Garbage, how should I throw it away? Ah, it hid.
あ、下に隠しちゃうタイプ？
Ah, the type that hides it underneath?
なんかさ、消しゴムとかさ、消しゴムとか下に隠すとどんどん溜まっていくのじゃ。
If you hide erasers underneath, they just keep piling up.
すごい美味しいお店見つけたんだけど。ねえ、聞いてんの！？
"I found a really delicious restaurant." "Hey, are you listening!?"
あ、あ、女の子怒ってる、怒ってる。ちょ、起きて起きて！
Ah, the girl is mad. Hey, wake up!
起きて起きて起きて！起きて起きて！
Wake up, wake up, wake up!
あ、うんうん言うのか。よしよしよしよし、うんうんうん。
Ah, you do say yeah. Good, yeah, yeah, yeah.
ぼ、僕が悪いよ、僕が悪い。もう漏れが悪い、漏れがすべて、漏れがすべて悪いです。
I'm at fault, everything is my fault, I'm entirely to blame.
ごめんなのじゃ、ごめんなのじゃ、すみませなのじゃ。
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I apologize.
もう何言われても平謝りすれば、あの、お姉ごの機嫌は直る！直らなくても、あの、平謝りしない方がより最悪な結果になるのじゃ。
Profusely apologizing is better than not apologizing.
でっかい、でっかいでっかいでっかい。でも、わかるのじゃ。
Huge, huge, huge. But I get it.
曲って、音って、でかければでかいほど良くて、音ってでかければでかいほど良いんじゃが、外で出すとね、迷惑じゃからね。
Music and sound, the louder the better, but it's a nuisance outside.
家で聴く分にはね、でかければでかいほど。
Listening to it at home, the louder the better.
今日はプレミアムフライデーだ。
Today is Premium Friday.
のじゃ。わしが偉い人？15時？はい、帰るよ、帰るよ！偉い人が帰れないと部下は帰れないというのじゃ。
Right. I'm the boss? 3 PM? If the boss can't leave, subordinates can't.
でもあるいは15時って早い？今日は彼女とデートだ！
Is 3 PM early? Today's a date with my girlfriend!
寿司。焼肉行きたいのじゃ。寿司怖いのでゃ。濡れてるし。
Sushi. I want yakiniku. Sushi is scary, and it's wet.
そこはかとなく……読めてるっぽい。
"Vaguely..." ...looks like it can be read.
うん、なかなか、なかなかいいんじゃなかろうか。のじゃ。寿司。焼肉食べたいのじゃ。好きなのじゃ。
Yeah, isn't this pretty good? Right. Sushi. I want yakiniku.
いくのじゃ！61問。
Let's go! Question 61.
あ、物理法則逃げられない。
Ah, the laws of physics are inescapable.
あ、止めまくっちゃだめみたいな。食べたいのだけ食べよう。サーモン！卵好き！エビは食べない。これも知らないから食べない。卵好きなのじゃ。サーモンと卵だけ食べるのじゃ。
Let's just eat what I want. Salmon! I like eggs! I don't eat shrimp.
お手本拝借。お手本早く来た。よお〜お、ポンって言ったら手を叩いてね。
Borrowing the example. When it says "pon", clap your hands.
ずるなのじゃ！これ人間がずる、人間が悪いのか。悪意を持っているのじゃ！
That's cheating! This human is cheating, they've got malice!
お前の弁当温め中。あ、あるあるですのじゃ。こういうのはね、横に置いてあげるとね、いいのじゃ。
"Warming your bento." Ah, placing it aside is good.
行くのじゃ。あ、歌ってる。
Let's go. Ah, they're singing.
帰ってきたぜ鳥取ー！のじゃー！！砂丘サイコリー！サハラよりデカリー！い、いーよ！言い過ぎなのじゃ！
"We're back in Tottori!" "Sakyu's awesome!" "Bigger than the Sahara!" Too far!
いや、言い過ぎ、だめなのじゃ！言い過ぎなの言い過ぎなのじゃ持ち上げすぎなのじゃ。
No, going too far is bad! You're hyping it up too much.
今日は彼女とデートだ。ガンダムの見た目してるロボットアニメ見るのじゃ。
Today's a date with my girlfriend. Watching a robot anime.
さっきのエンターが悪いのか。ノリづらいこと言うエンターは良くないのじゃ。
Was the enterer from earlier bad? Hard-to-get-into entertainers are no good.
こと考えてないのよ。
I wasn't really thinking about it.
ほどよく読めてるっぽい。
It reads pretty well.
なかなかいいんじゃなかろうか。
I'd say that's pretty good.
第66問。
Question 66.
え、頭でか！
Whoa, huge head!
ちょ、失礼します。
Wait, let me slip through.
失礼します。
Let me slip through.
失礼しますのよ。
一番後ろの席！
Taking the very back seat!
一番後ろの席取るのよ。
でかいのよ、でかいのよ！
That's huge! That's huge!
第67問。
Question 67.
先頭。
Vanguard.
え、シャアいる、シャア。
There's Chaa, there's Chaa.
赤いの、赤いの。
There's Akai, there's Akai.
あ、でもシャアが後ろにいるということは？
Wait, if Chaa is in the back,
シャア作じゃないのに乗るのよ。
Why are you riding when you're not even Chaa?
第68問。
Question 68.
お前、後ろの敵なんとかして！
Hey, do something about the enemies in the back!
了解なのよ！
Got it!
わしのプリーズきゃー！
Watch the please, c'mon!
あ、いけた？
Ah, did I make it?
いけたんじゃない？
Didn't I make it?
のよー！
No way!
上映中。
Screening in progress.
第70問。
Question 70.
あー、渋いのかっこいいの！
Oh, that's edgy!
なんかすごいかっこいいトークが行われるのよ。
That's some seriously cool talk.
あからさまに…
So dashing...
…読めてるっぽい。
It reads kinda cool.
え、すごい！
Oh, amazing!
え、めっちゃ空気を読めててすごいのだ。
Reading the mood so well, that's amazing!
すごいのだ。
That's amazing!
すごいのだ、すごいのだ。
That's amazing, that's amazing!
えね、わしも、わしもこれやりたい！
Hey, I want to do that too!
わしもこれやりたい！
I want to do that too!
わしも、さあ、
I want to...
シュッ。
Shh...
バーでさ、かっこいい大人のバーでさ、あのシュッ、
At a cool adult bar, like,
「あちらのお客様からでして」ってのやりたいのよ。
"From that customer over there..."
どうしたらできる？どうしたらできる？
How do you do that? How do you do that?
え、でもさ、それをするにはさ、あの、少なくともさ、じゃあ、
To do that, you have to, um...
あの、事前にさ、打ち合わせをしてさ、きっと、
Well, you coordinate in advance,
なんか食べログとかで予約するときのさ、なんか備考欄とかにさ、
like when you make a reservation on Tabelog or somewhere,
あの「シュッてやるやつをやりたいので、あの、協力していただけませんか？」みたいなさ、
"Could you please do the 'shh' thing?"
そういうのをさ、仕込んでから行かないといけないんじゃなかろうか。
you've gotta plan all that out, don't you think?
だめ、かな。
Maybe not.
お酒飲めないのよ。
Can I drink alcohol?
飲めるけどそんな強くないのよ。
I can drink, but not very strongly.
弱めではあるのよ。
It's on the weaker side, though.
だからお外では飲まんのよ。
So I don't drink outside.
バーとかでも飲まんのよ。
I don't drink at bars either.
ヘロヘロになっちゃうから。
I'd get all floppy.
お水飲むのよ。
I'm a water drinker.
水が大好きなのよ。
I love water.
水と、水とお茶が好きなのよ。
I love water and tea.
おうちでもお酒飲まないのよ。
I don't drink alcohol at home either.
なんかお友達が、お酒を飲んで、
It's like when friends drink
深刻な相談をしたそうなときとか。
and have serious consultations.
なんか深刻な話とか、そういうので、あ、
Like, serious talks and stuff like that—
空気読み、空気読みしてますのよ！
Wait, reading the air, reading the air!
空気読みしてますのよ！
Reading the air!
なんか、今日は、あの、つらそうな子がいたら、じゃあわしも付き合うかみたいなやつ？
Like, "If there's someone feeling down today, maybe I should hang out with them?"
そういうのはする。
I do that.
え、わし超人間。
Hey, I'm super human.
わし超人間なのだ！
I'm a super human!
行くのよ。
I'm going.
空気読みさ迷うんだな。
Reading the air and wandering off.
ん？何？必勝。
Huh? What? Victory?
え、なんか右でさ、右にめっちゃ見てる人いる。
Hey, someone on the right is...
なんかすごい、ん？
Someone is staring really hard.
なのだ？
What?
何が起き、なの？
What just happened?
なんで鍋スッカスカなん…？
Why is the pot completely empty?
食べ物が届くまでもうすこしのぼうだ…！
Be patient until the food arrives...!
あ、子供が。
Ah, the children!
子供の未来のために、のじゃー！
For the children's future, no way!
わしのプレイスキルが。
My play skills...
ゲームクリアしたのばっかりに。
Right after clearing the game!
わしのプレイスキルが。
My play skills!
カーブを落としてるのに、全然できないのよ。
Even though I dropped the bar, I still couldn't do it!
明日は彼女とデートだ。
Tomorrow is a date with my girlfriend.
明日の受験でオレの人生が決まる…。
Tomorrow's exam will decide my life...
明日の武道館1stライブ成功しますように…。
May tomorrow's Budokan 1st live be a success...
台風、気圧なのだ。
Typhoon, atmospheric pressure!
気圧やじゃのう。
It's an atmospheric pressure typhoon!
お、お、お、何何！お前、お前、お前何すんのじゃ！おい！おい！
Wait, wait, wait! Hey, hey, what is this?!
い、ちょちょちょちょちょ、え、え、ど、ど、どうしたらいい？え！
Hey, what should I do?!
はぁ…。
Ah...
自然災害には逆らえないのよ。
You can't fight natural disasters!
なに？
What?
白馬の王子様に助けてもらうことが私の夢なの…！
My dream is to be saved by a prince on a white horse...
あ、いいの。
Ah, good.
まおうのしろ、きいろでじょう。
The Demon King's White Castle.
けいばじょう。
Racecourse.
まおうのしろあぶないよ。
The Demon King's castle is dangerous.
けいばじょうもあぶない。
The racecourse is also dangerous.
競馬場、ね、競馬場行ったことないからわかんない！
Racecourse... wait, I've never been to a racecourse, so I don't know!
競馬場行ったことない！
I've never been to a racecourse!
いないの？
Is there no one?
城下町だったらさ、いるいないのじゃ？
If it's a castle town, surely someone's there, right?
城下町、いない？いないの？
Is there really no one?
城下、
Castle town...
うま、うま、って言ってたよ。うま、って言ってたよ。
Wait, she said "horse", didn't she?
うまじゃろ。
It must be "horse".
助けてもらうのが目的だから魔王城？
The goal is to save her, so... Demon King?
え、あざとくない？それかなり。
Isn't that a bit too subtle?
それかなり作詞じゃん。
That's practically the lyric, right?
確かにピーチ姫っていつも捕まってるしの。
I mean, Peach-姫 always gets caught, you know.
人間は可愛い女の子を助けたい？助けたいと思う。
People want to save cute girls, you'd think.
わしが、わしが魔王城行ったら助けてくれる？
If I go to the Demon King's castle, would they save me?
わしも魔王城行こうかな。
Should I go to the Demon King's castle, too?
試し行動じゃん！
Let's try testing it out!
試してるのじゃ！ねえ！
That's trying it out! Hey!
ねえ、助かりたいからってさ、
Hey, wanting to be saved isn't...
さらわれたとかさ、深考力じゃなくてさ、助かりたい、助けてもらいたいを動機でさ、
It's not out of deep devotion, but rather the selfish urge of wanting to be saved and rescued—
あの魔王城行くのってかなり試してるのじゃ。
Going to the Demon King's castle is quite the trial run.
試し行動は嫌われるのじゃ。
Trial actions are disliked, you know.
良くないのじゃ。
That's not good.
それは、
That's...
うん、うん。それはお主が悪いなのだじゃ。
You are the one in the wrong.
お主が悪いよ。
You're in the wrong here!
のだじゃ。
Na-ja!
いくのだじゃ。
Let's go, na-ja!
あ、ライブなのだじゃ。
Ah, it's a live stream, na-ja!
よーいしょ。
Yoo-hoo!
こういうね、こういうの、応援うれしいですから。
I'm so happy when viewers show up!
こういうの応援うれしいですから。
こういうね、ファンの人間、あ、あ、あ、ファンの主らがね、
Knowing that fans have this sense of solidarity...
一体感を持ってね、盛り上げてくれてるってのはすごくうれしいのじゃ。
Really makes me happy to see them hyping it up together.
仮装大会！
Costume Contest!
あ、わしの一点でいけるってやつ？
Ah, you could win with just one point, right?
でもそれはこの子のためになんないと思うのじゃ。
But I feel like that wouldn't do much for this kid.
うん。だめなものはだめなのじゃ。
Yeah, no is no.
ひとりでやってるの？点数あげてよ。あ、
"You doing this alone? Give me some points!" Oh.
あ、こういうのを言ったらあげるのじゃ。
Oh, if they say things like this, I'll give them points.
たーーだーー！
Ta-da!
ゴウカクだよー！
You passed!
確かに。確かに。
True. True.
こういうMCの後あげるならありなのじゃ。
Giving points after an MC makes sense.
最初からあげるのはちょっと…
Giving them from the start is a bit...
ちょっとのじゃ。
A bit, you know.
こういう成功体験は別にいいのじゃ。
This kind of success is fine, you know.
押すなよ、絶対押すなよ。
Don't push! Definitely don't push!
あ、押して押して！
Ah, push it, push it!
なーー！
Noooo!
あ。
Ah...
あつくない。
It's not hot.
ん？熱い！
Huh? It's hot!
やめてくださいよ！熱いのだじゃ、熱いのだじゃ！
Stop it, it's too hot, it's too hot!
どう感じているかなんて関係ないのじゃ！
How it feels has nothing to do with it, you know!
面白ければなんでもいいのじゃ！
As long as it's funny, anything goes, you know!
のだじゃ、のだじゃ、のだじゃ、のだじゃ！
Na-ja, na-ja, na-ja, na-ja!
いくのだじゃ。
Here we go, na-ja.
業界に詳しいA子さん（仮名）。
Industry-savvy A-ko-san (pseudonym).
何？絶対詳しくないやろ。
What? She definitely doesn't know much!
絶対嘘やろ。
That's totally a lie!
あ、もうサイコをかけてあげるのね。
Ah, giving her a nice mosaic censoring!
はい、はい、はい、はい、はい。なるほどなのだじゃ。
I see, I see.
わかってきたのだじゃ。
I get it now.
ふん、ふん、ふん、ふん、ふん。
Hmm, hmm, hmm...
のだじゃ。熱いのじゃ。
Na-ja, it's hot, na-ja.
すごい、ピクチカしてる。
She's twitching so much!
首折れる。
Her neck is snapping!
この角度で親指に落ちたら、熱くなくても危なくなくても危ないのじゃ。
If you fall in at this angle, even if it's not hot, it's still dangerous!
しかもさ、若い若い子どもとかじゃったらさ、体柔らかいからい、から大丈夫かもじゃけどさ、
Plus, you know, young children doing this would probably be fine since their bodies are so soft and flexible, but—
あの、大人がこれやるとガチで骨折するのじゃ。
When adults do this, it genuinely snaps bones!
骨折しちゃうのじゃ！
You can fracture your bones!
よし、次いきますのだじゃ。
Alright, let's move on to the next one, na-ja.
のだじゃ。
Na-ja!
第81問。
Question 81.
アイドルB子ちゃんが始球式を行います。
Idol B-ko-chan is performing the ceremonial first pitch.
のだじゃ。
Na-ja!
頑張って打つよ。
Do your best to pitch!
来た。プレスキル、プレスキル来た。
Here it comes. A pre-skill, a pre-skill is coming!
よし、よし。
Alright, alright.
はっ！来たーー！
Hah! It's a hit!
当たったのだじゃ。
It was a hit, na-ja!
暗殺教室で野球を覚えたのじゃ。
Learning baseball through assassination classroom, na-ja.
何？
What?
のだじゃ？のだじゃ？
Na-ja? Na-ja?
何？これ何？
What? What is this?
元ネタ知らんないのじゃ。
I have no idea what the source material is, na-ja.
ん？寝取ダメ？なんで？なんで？なんで？なんで？
Wait, is it "cuckold"? Why? Why? Why? Why?
まもなく山頂だ…。
Almost at the summit...
まもなく山頂。
Almost at the summit.
何？これは？
What? What is this?
これは何がいけないの？
Why is this no good?
何が起きているのだじゃ？
What is happening, na-ja?
何が起きているの？
What is happening?
わし山行かないから知らんわ。
I don't know because I never go to the mountains.
あ、熊危ない。
Oh, a bear! That's dangerous!
ちゅ、ちゅ、ちゅ、死んだふり、死んだふり。
Play dead, play dead!
でも死んだふりしちゃだめなのじゃ。
Playing dead is no good, na-ja.
熊は死んだふりしちゃだめ。
Bears—playing dead is no good.
あの、背中を、背中を向けずに後ずさりなのじゃ。
You have to back away without turning your back to it!
背中を向けずに後ずさり。
Backing away without turning your back!
死んだふりなんて今の熊には通じないのじゃ。
Playing dead doesn't work on bears nowadays, na-ja.
できるだけ自然界にない音を出しながら背中を向けて後ずさり。
Try to make as little unnatural noise as possible while backing away with your back...
でもどうしてもやばいときは、あの、
Wait, if it's really dangerous, you...
あの、首を、首を守って、あの、小さくなるのじゃ、前屈み。首を守って小さくなって、あの、
Protect your neck and shrink down—get into a child's pose.
何？だ、ダンゴムシの、ダンゴムシのポーズをとるのじゃ。
What? Do the dung beetle—the dung beetle pose!
あの、首、首、急所を下げるのじゃ。
Protect your neck and lower your vital spots, na-ja.
熊はガチで怖いのだじゃ。
Bears are seriously terrifying, na-ja.
天敵なのだじゃ
It's our natural enemy.
山で暮らしている時の天敵、熊、普通にめちゃくちゃ怖かったのだじゃ
Bears, our natural enemy when living in the mountains, were just insanely terrifying.
危なかったのだじゃ。うん。
It was dangerous. Yeah.
怖いのじゃ。
It's scary.
水飲むのじゃ。
Time to drink water.
チチが買ってきてくれたんだじゃ
Dad bought and brought this for me.
なんか甘味舐めたのじゃ
Somehow I wanted to lick some sweets.
いくのじゃ
Let's go.
え、シートベルト良くないのじゃ？シートベルトするのじゃ？ちょいちょいちょい
Huh, seatbelts are bad? You should wear a seatbelt? Wait, wait, wait.
危ないのじゃ。
That's dangerous.
絶対に好都合席で居ろうとも、どんな時で居ろうともシートベルトはするのじゃ。危ないのじゃ。死んじゃう。
No matter if it's the passenger seat or whatever time it is, you gotta wear your seatbelt. It's dangerous. You'll die.
ライフ1つしかない人間。
Humans only have one life.
あの、ね、この保護者参観のときにね、あの自信なさげに
Uh, you know, during this parent-teacher observation, looking unconfident...
いいこと。左見てる。
Good. Looking left.
あ、右を見る。左を見る。
Ah, look right. Look left.
右を見る。左を見る。
Look right. Look left.
みんな早いのだじゃ！みんな早いのだじゃ！
Everyone's so fast! Everyone's so fast!
あ、UFO！UFO！UFO！UFO！UFO！UFO！いるのじゃ！
Ah, UFO! UFO! UFO! UFO! UFO! UFO! There it is!
何？何々？今何が起きたのじゃ？
What? What just happened?
UFOすごいのだじゃ。ソフィア、捕まえるのじゃ！
UFO is amazing. Sophia, catch it!
あ、出た。ナロウKあるある。ナロウKあるある。カップルを助けて！カップルを助けて！
Ah, there it is. Narou-kei cliché. Narou-kei cliché. Save the couple! Save the couple!
宇宙人「質問ニ、YESナラ手ヲ上ゲロ。NOナラ手ヲ下ゲロ。」了解なのじゃ。行くのじゃ。
Alien: "Question 2: Raise your hand for YES, lower your hand for NO." Understood. Let's go.
宇宙人「地球ヲ滅ボサレタクナケレバ空気ヲ読メ。」了解？
Alien: "If you don't want Earth destroyed, read the room." Understood?
宇宙人「オ前ハ地球人カ？」まあ、そうなのじゃ。
Alien: "Are you an Earthling?" Well, yeah.
宇宙人「地球ヲ滅ボサレタクナイ」
Alien: "Earth I don't want it destroyed"
宇宙人「地球ヲ滅ボ…あ、あ、や、声出さないで！」
Alien: "Earth desu... Ah, ah, wait, don't use your voice!"
宇宙人「オトトイノ、アシタハ、アサッテノ、サキオトツイ」
Alien: "The day before yesterday, tomorrow is the day after tomorrow, three days ago..."
宇宙人「オ前ハ痩セテイリカ？」痩せていない！いない！痩せていない！痩せていない！
Alien: "Are you losing weight?" I'm not losing weight! Not at all!
宇宙人「ココデ何カラ見タカ？」何見てるの！1回上げたら下げれないのじゃ！ねえ、1回上げたら下げらんない！
Alien: "What did you see here?" What are you looking at! Once you raise it, you can't lower it! Hey, once you raise it, you can't lower it!
宇宙人「秘密ハ守レルカ？」秘密は守れる！守れるのだじゃ！ねえ、ねえ、の、の、のじゃー！
Alien: "Can you keep secrets?" I can keep secrets! I can keep them! Hey, hey, no, no, no jaaa!
宇宙人「カユイツコロハアリマスカ？」か、か、かゆいところ？か、かゆいところ…ある言っても止めてくんないのじゃ。
Alien: "Is there any itching place?" Itchy spot? Even if I say yes, they won't stop!
宇宙人「オ前ニ地球ヲ守ルヒーローヲヤッテモラウ」え、かっこいいやつ、やっぱナロウ系なのじゃ。え、どうやって下げたらいいの？
Alien: "We want you to play the hero protecting Earth." Huh, a cool guy, after all it's Narou-kei. Eh, how do I lower it?
なんか何にもできずに終わったのだじゃ。人生のよ…
It ended without doing anything. Like life...
人生は何かもらしとげてほしいのじゃ！そうだな！
I want you to accomplish something in life! That's right!
何もできずに終わった！わし、わしのナロウ系が、わしのナロウ系失敗！わしの、わしのナロウ系失敗なのじゃー！のじゃー！
It ended without doing anything! My, my Narou-kei, my Narou-kei failed! My, my Narou-kei failed! No jaaa!
キャー助けてー！
Aaah, help me!
おー！変身してる！すごい！変身してる！
Oh! Transforming! Amazing! Transforming!
声はシジ、シジじゃよ。
Voice is Shiji, it's Shiji.
今のがすぐついた書き込むんだから！だめなのじゃ！なんでやねん！アホちゃうか！
Because you immediately write down whatever just appeared! That's no good! Why is that! Are you an idiot!
エスカレーターはだめじゃよ。危ないから。絶対に動かないのじゃ。絶対に。だって歩くほうが早いもん。うん。
Escalators are no good. Because it's dangerous. You must never move. Never. Because walking is faster. Yeah.
議題、あのバンドの今後の方向性、解散、ボーカルソロデビュー。
Agenda: Future direction of that band, disbandment, vocal solo debut.
下をね？
Look down, right?
あ、出た！さっきすべってたバンド。
Ah, there it is! The band that slipped earlier.
演奏力を見せてほしいのじゃ！行くのじゃ！
Show us your musical skills! Let's go!
ベースってこの世の楽器で一番かっこよくて
The bass is the coolest instrument in this world and
俺のばあちゃんがポックリ逝ったぜ！
My grandma kicked the bucket!
え、そういうのは令和にはふさわしくないのじゃ。
Eh, that kind of stuff isn't appropriate for Reiwa.
え、そういうのも令和にはふさわしくないのじゃ。不安を煽ることはやめてほしいのじゃ。
Eh, that kind of stuff isn't appropriate for Reiwa either. I'd want you to stop stirring up anxiety.
これがいいと思ってるなら
If you think this is good,
世間に鈍感すぎなのじゃ。今の時代を見って売り出さないと誰にも見てもらえませんのじゃ。
You're too insensitive to society. If you don't look at the current times and market yourself, nobody will look at you.
節電中。
Power saving in progress.
あ、髪の目が
Ah, the hair...
もうちょいもうちょい優しく。のじゃ。
A bit more, a bit more gently. No-ja.
ふんふんふん
Hm, hm, hm.
そこはかとなく
"Somehow or other..."
最後何が起きた？
What happened at the end?
最後何が起きたのじゃ？
What happened at the end, pray tell?
のじゃ？
Huh?
いけた？
Did it work?
96問！
Question 96!
今日絶対に座るぞ。
I'm definitely getting a seat today.
何？
What?
最初からこういとこ座っとくのじゃ。
You should just sit here from the very beginning.
あ、
Ah.
のじゃ？
Huh?
ヒマだな…
I'm so bored...
久しぶりに惑星でも…
Maybe I'll ravage a planet for a change...
いややっぱヒーローバトル見たいからさの、バトル見たい！戦いたいじゃろ！何も無いものを殲滅したとてそれが本当に快楽になるか？いや、ならない！
No, I want to see a hero battle! I want to see a battle! You want to fight, don't you? Does annihilating nothing really bring true pleasure? No, it doesn't!
第98問
Question 98.
強き者と戦うこと、そして戦って勝つことこそがのじゃー！
Fighting the strong, and winning that fight, that's what it's all about!
強すぎたのじゃ。
That was way too strong.
人間弱い。
Humans are so weak.
人間弱いのだ。
えっ、感動的なシーン。
Huh, a touching scene.
久しぶり
It's been a while.
来てくれたんだ…
You came to see me...
ずっと会いたかったんだよ。
I've wanted to see you all this time.
もっと強く手を握ってて。
Hold my hand tighter.
懐かしいな、この感じ。
This feels so nostalgic.
何？エモパート来たのじゃ？
What? Are we in an emotional part now?
心霊写真を写メでくれたよね。
You sent me a photo of a ghost picture, didn't you?
アレ、携帯の待ち受けにしてんだよ。
I've got that as my phone wallpaper.
いや、違う、悪事じゃないか。
Wait no, isn't that a misdeed?
こういう最後の時ならどんなささいなことでもそれがその子の思い出になる。
At a final moment like this, even the smallest thing becomes their cherished memory.
そうかも、それを笑うのは失礼なのじゃ。
True, laughing at that would be rude.
全部知ってるんだからね。
Because I know everything, you see.
もっと一緒にいればよかったな。
I wish we could've stayed together longer.
病気なのかな。
Are they sick?
怪獣ってホントにいるんだね。
Monsters really do exist, huh.
私つぶされちゃったよ。
I got crushed.
つぶされちゃった？
You got crushed?
私と初めて会った日、覚えてる？
Do you remember the day we first met?
あなた優柔不断だから、
You're so indecisive,
私のことは忘れて、
So forget about me
早く新しい人を見つけてね。
And find someone new quickly.
恋人じゃ！
A lover, huh!
空気読めなくてごめんね、わしのせいで結末が...
Sorry for not reading the room, because of me the ending...
そんな、いつも周りの人に気配りできる、
Even so, you're always considerate of those around you,
優しいあなたが大好きだったよ。
And I loved your kind self so much.
え、そんな、わしのせい？でも空気なんて読まなくていい時も
Eh, really? My fault? But even when you don't need to read the room
あることを忘れないでね。
Don't forget that there are times like that too.
ありがとう...
Thank you...
え、わしのせいで1人の人...空気を読まないと
Huh, because of me, one person... If you don't read the room
死にたくないよ...人を殺しかねない？
I don't want to die... could it end up killing someone?
そんな、悲しいのじゃ...悲しいのじゃ...
Oh, how sad... how sad...
え、バタフライエフェクトってやつ？ん？直接的にわしが殺しちゃった？
Huh, is this the butterfly effect? Huh? Did I directly kill them?
第100問
Question 100.
何に？
What?
あ、最後のね、最後のね
Ah, the last one, the last one
のじゃー！なんとはなしに読めてるっぽい。えー！最後、最後わしバットエンドにしちゃったの？バットエンドにしちゃったのじゃ？
Oh! It seems like I read the room somehow. Eh! Did I make the ending a bad end? Did I make it a bad end?!
悲しいのじゃ...悲しいのじゃ...
So sad... so sad...
総合結果見るのじゃ。
Let's check the comprehensive results.
え、なんかあんまり高く無い。そんな。
Eh, it's not very high. Seriously.
え？なんか、なんか、なんか微妙な、なんか微妙な嫁なさ、それが一番傷つくのじゃ！微妙な、微妙な、微妙な、微妙な嫁なさななのじゃ！
Eh? Some, some, somehow a subtle, a subtle read-the-room score, that hurts the most! A subtle, subtle, subtle read-the-room score!
えー？わし人間、人間まだだめ？わしカメレオンなのじゃ？
Huh? Me, human? Am I still not good enough? Am I a chameleon?
サラマンダーな上に、サラマンダーなのにカメレオン？これから人カメレオンで生きていくのじゃ？わしはカメレオンですのじゃ。
On top of being a salamander, a chameleon despite being a salamander? From now on I'll live as a human-chameleon? I am a chameleon, you see.
おしまいなのだ... なのじゃー！
It's the end... No, wait!
難しいのじゃー！人間に溶け込むのめちゃくちゃ難しかったのじゃ。カメレオン皮膚けないよでも。皮膚けないのじゃ。元の部屋に
It was so hard! Blending in with humans was crazy difficult. But a chameleon can't shed its skin. It can't shed it. Back to the original room
のじゃー！
Noja!
なんか難しかったのじゃ。
That was pretty difficult, wasn't it?
もっと空気を読むって簡単なのかなと思ってたけど、
I thought reading the room would be simple,
人間って考えること多いの。
but people think about so many things!
てかわし思ったんだが、空気を読むのって何が難しいかって話をしてい？
Well, I had this thought though. What's so hard about reading the room, you ask?
空気を読むためにはまずその、その場における正解を、その共通認識、その場にある共通認識をなんか正しく認識しておかなきゃいけないじゃろ？
To read the room, you first need to correctly understand the "correct answer" in that situation—
それって知識でえじゃない？
Isn't that about knowledge?
それって経験とかさ、経験に基づくさ、知識ゲーでさ、
Or experience, or trivia based on experience, like...
なんか人間界のさ、空気を読むってさ、誰も教えてくんないのじゃ、ちっちゃい頃とかじゃとさ、なんかその空気を読めないとさ、はぶかれるとかさ、そういう目に遭ってね、空気が読めないからこそ…
nobody teaches you how to read the room in human society when you're little.
なんか悪いこととかが分かりやすく起きるけど、
...bad things become easy to understand.
大人になったらもういちいち誰も指摘してくれなくなるから、
Once you're an adult, nobody points things out for you anymore.
なんか空気を読むってめちゃくちゃ高頭スキルなんじゃないの？ めちゃ難しくない？ 相手の心を感じる。
So reading the room is basically an advanced soft skill, isn't it? It's super hard!
思いやりとかってさ、できるだけさやってるつもりなんじゃけど、
Trying to be considerate is something we try our best to do, but...
やってるつもりなんじゃけどさ、なんかその知識がさ、ある程度ないとさ、難しくない？
...if you don't have a certain amount of knowledge, it's really hard, right?
人間のことあんまり傷つけたくないのじゃ。傷つけたくないからできるだけ空気って読みたいけど、
You don't want to hurt people, so you want to read the room as much as possible, but...
習得するのがすごい難しいのじゃ。ね。
...mastering it is extremely difficult.
でその経験もさ、経験を積む環境と積まない環境があるじゃん。
And experience also depends on whether your environment lets you build it up.
どうしたらいいのじゃ？ どこにいたら適切な経験が積めるのじゃ？
So what should you do? Where can you go to build the right experience?
ある程度集団の中に属さないと、そういう空気を読むための訓練ってできない気がするのじゃ。
You have to belong to a group to train for that kind of reading, I guess.
でもわしコミュニケーションのこと暗記ゲーだと思っているよ、正直。
But honestly, I think of communication as memory training.
なんかあ、これしたら人間喜ぶんだとか、これしたら人間悲しむのかとか、
Like, if I do this, people get happy, or if I do that, people get sad.
あ、こういうこと言うと人間は嫌な気持ちになるらしいとか、なんかそういうのをね覚えて覚えるたびに修正はしてるんじゃが、なかなか…
Learning those things and trying to correct them as I go is still pretty tough.
なかなか難しいのじゃ。
...it's really difficult.
サインをしき、野球のサインをしき。野球のサインをしきって何なのだじゃ？
Like, baseball signals... what even are baseball signals?
なんか女性声優さんとかが、あ 先輩もやってた！ 先輩もやってた？ やつ？
Some female voice actors and seniors have done it too!
なんかそういう、なんじゃろな、特定の分野、例えばアニメとかさ、このアニメを知らないと読めない空気とかさ、そのガンダムを知らないとどっち選べばいいかわかんないとかあったじゃろ？
If you don't know specific anime or Gundam, you miss the vibe and don't know which to pick.
そういうさ、なんかその特定のコンテンツに触れてないと読めない空気ってのが結構あると思うんじゃよ。それって難しくない？
So if you haven't experienced those popular contents, you miss the vibe.
だから餅人間たちは人気コンテンツを見たり履修したりするんじゃろな。
That's why people look at popular content and study it.
なんか、なんじゃろ、流行ってるドラマを見るとか流行ってる映画を見るだとかって、そのトークテーマ、トークテーマとしてその…
Like watching trendy dramas or movies, which are often used as conversation topics.
時事ネタみたいなの、ノックアウトかみたいなのもあるかもじゃけど、なんかそれ以上に太っとした時に空気を読むために…
...slang or punchlines come up, but beyond that, when you're just living your life,
習得してる？ 人間が社会で社会的に生きていくために頑張ってるんじゃな。
...you build up your skills so you aren't left out when social interactions happen.
だから倍速で見る若者がいる。なるほどね！
That's why some young people watch things at double speed. Makes sense!
じゃあ別にそのコンテンツ自身に興味があるというよりか、コンテンツじゃなくて、ブレから省かれないように、知識としてつけておくみたいなの。
So it's not really about having a personal interest in the content itself, but rather acquiring it as knowledge so you don't miss out.
へえー、いろんな、それはもう果たして楽しみ方なのかと言われると微妙なんじゃが。
Ohhh... Is that really an enjoyable way to experience things? That's a bit subtle, though.
でも、群れに属すメリットって結構いっぱいあるから、あるし…
Well, you know, human society... but there are plenty of benefits to belonging to a group.
やっぱひとりぼっちわ寂しいから
Being all alone is lonely, after all,
人間ではないものな うん、そうだな 人間かぁ
not that you're human... Yeah, true.
Human, huh.
こんばんはのはじめての見知らぬようなのじゃ！ひとりと繋がった。それは孤立してはみだしたに見える
Good evening to you, as if meeting for the first time!
Connected with someone. It might look isolated,
馴染める人は望めないのさ サラマンダーの場合わね 孤立にわ孤立の意味があるのじゃ
but fitting in isn't hoped for.
In the salamander's case, isolation has meaning.
だからなんか、例えばいま職場で阿智メラが大流行していたとして
So like, for example, if Achimera were
all the rage at your workplace right now,
いまね、もしね、お主の職場で阿智メラが大流行していたとして、職場の人にすすめられたから
if, say, Achimera was super popular
at your workplace, and someone recommended it,
そのトークでっけ、トークでっけのために阿智メラの配信見てみるかって人がこん中にいるかもしれないけど
you might have people checking out the stream
just to join the conversation,
わし的にはそれも十分社会的な行動だと思うのじゃ。 うん。
but from my perspective,
that's also fully social behavior. Yeah.
で、その義務感で見ている人間がいたとして、そういう人間にも好きになってもらえるように頑張ろうって思うのじゃ。うん。
And supposing someone watches out of a sense of duty,
I want them to come to like me too. Yeah.
なんか、興味ないけど義務感で見たけど、意外とおもろいやんとか意外と好きやんって思ってもらえる
Even with no interest, watching out of duty,
wanting them to think, "This is surprisingly fun,"
ように頑張ろうと思うのじゃ。 うん。でも、やっぱ好きだからで見るのがやっぱり一番いい感情
wanting to work hard for that. Yeah.
Still, watching because you like it is best,
いいことだと思う。健康にも、精神的にもね。いいと思うから
I think it's a good thing for both
health and mentality. Because I think it's good,
楽しんでみてもらえると嬉しいの。 うん。
I'd be happy if you could enjoy watching. Yeah.
だからずっと好きでいてもらえるように頑張ろうと思うのじゃ。 うん。
So I'll do my best so you can keep liking me. Yeah.
なんか興味ないけど義務感で見たけど意外とおもろいやんとか意外と好きやんって思ってもらえるように
Even if you watched out of obligation, wanting
you to think it's surprisingly fun or likable,
頑張ろうと思うのじゃ。 うん。そう思うのじゃ。 うん。
wanting to work hard. Yeah.
That's what I think. Yeah.
今日はこのへんでおしまいにお仕事... はっ！
Well, that's about it for today,
let's wrap it up and work... Ah!
あしたの配信告知をするのじゃ！
I have tomorrow's stream announcement!
あしたの19時からはこちら、
Tomorrow starting at 19:00,
it's right here:
阿智メラのインターネット防災訓練！
Achimera's Internet Disaster
Prevention Training!
インターネットを使うにおいて気をつけたほうがいいこと、サラマンダーが体当たりで得た知識をお主らに教授していこうと、教えてあげようと思いますのじゃ。
Things to keep in mind when using the internet,
passing on knowledge gained firsthand.
インターネットリテラシーのお勉強なのじゃ。
It's an internet literacy study session.
わしとともに防災訓練をしよう。19時から、あしたの19時から行いますのじゃ。
Let's do disaster prevention training together.
Starting tomorrow at 19:00.
まだスライドの準備してないから、今日配信終わったら
I haven't prepared the slides yet,
so once today's stream ends,
すっごい頑張って準備しようと思いますのじゃ。
I'm going to work super hard
to get them ready.
いい配信にできるように頑張るのじゃ！あしたも遊びに来てほしいのじゃ！
I'll do my best to make it a great stream!
I want you to come play tomorrow too!
レイドってどうやってやるのかの？ちょっと調べていい？ちょっとお主らも待っててくれる？やり方がわかんないのじゃ。
How do you do a raid? Can I check?
Can you guys wait? I don't know how.
あ,これ！のじゃ！こ,こなんじゃない？できた！よいしょ。
Ah, this! Is it like this?
I did it! Here we go.
やり方わかった！ソピアの枠にお主らを飛ばすのじゃ。なんか昨日遊びにいきたいのメンバーがやってていいなって思ってわしもやってみたいって思ったからやってみようと思うのじゃ。
I get how! Sending you to Sopia's stream.
Some friends did it yesterday, I wanted to try it.
うん！やってみますのじゃ。じゃあ今日の配信はこれで終わりですのじゃ！また次の配信で会いたいのだ。
Yeah! Let's give it a try.
That's it for today! See you next time.
おわりの挨拶は、えっと、さらばじゃあで。さらばじゃあでおしまいにしますのじゃ。
For the closing greeting, um, "saraba jaa".
We'll wrap it up with "saraba jaa".
いくのじゃ！それではお主ら、さらばじゃあ！
Let's go!
Well then everyone, farewell!